<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-05-22T20:59:05+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rising Embedded Mx</title><subtitle>This is my world, where I can do what I think
</subtitle><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">OpenBLT successfully deployed on the Bluepill Plus board!</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2025/05/22/openBLT-bluepill.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OpenBLT successfully deployed on the Bluepill Plus board!" /><published>2025-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2025/05/22/openBLT-bluepill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2025/05/22/openBLT-bluepill.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m back at it—programming, writing code, and, well… negotiating time with my girlfriend (she’s not a huge fan of how many hours I spend on this stuff 😅). Anyway, over the past few weeks, I’ve been working on adapting OpenBLT to a Bluepill Plus board.</p>

<p>It wasn’t exactly a walk in the park. I hadn’t touched microcontrollers in over five months, so getting back into the groove took some effort. The bootloader migration itself only took about three or four days to get up and running, but documenting everything? That’s where I really struggled. I felt rusty—and honestly, even remembering how to use Jekyll to write this blog was a small adventure in itself.</p>

<p>After so many hours of programming, testing, and writing, I finally got the bootloader working on my Bluepill Plus board! 🎉</p>

<p>If you’re curious, you can check out the full project on my <a href="https://github.com/razielgdn/black-and-blue-pill-plus-with-openBLT">Github repo</a>.</p>

<p>I also put together a small tutorial on <a href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/projects/en/1-openblt/openblt-bluepill">this site</a>, where I walk through the steps I followed to migrate the bootloader.</p>

<p>The goal behind this is to lay the foundation for flashing software via CAN in a network of microcontrollers—managing sensors, actuators, motors, or whatever your project needs. All with low-cost boards and free tools.
I believe that freedom shouldn’t only apply to software, but to hardware too.</p>

<p>Because everyone should have access to technology—especially in the kind of solarpunk future where innovation works with nature, not against it.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="STM32F103" /><category term="ARM Cortex M3" /><category term="blog" /><category term="free software" /><category term="free hardware" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m back at it—programming, writing code, and, well… negotiating time with my girlfriend (she’s not a huge fan of how many hours I spend on this stuff 😅). Anyway, over the past few weeks, I’ve been working on adapting OpenBLT to a Bluepill Plus board. It wasn’t exactly a walk in the park. I hadn’t touched microcontrollers in over five months, so getting back into the groove took some effort. The bootloader migration itself only took about three or four days to get up and running, but documenting everything? That’s where I really struggled. I felt rusty—and honestly, even remembering how to use Jekyll to write this blog was a small adventure in itself. After so many hours of programming, testing, and writing, I finally got the bootloader working on my Bluepill Plus board! 🎉 If you’re curious, you can check out the full project on my Github repo. I also put together a small tutorial on this site, where I walk through the steps I followed to migrate the bootloader. The goal behind this is to lay the foundation for flashing software via CAN in a network of microcontrollers—managing sensors, actuators, motors, or whatever your project needs. All with low-cost boards and free tools. I believe that freedom shouldn’t only apply to software, but to hardware too. Because everyone should have access to technology—especially in the kind of solarpunk future where innovation works with nature, not against it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I need a Job Now!</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2025/05/04/sabatic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I need a Job Now!" /><published>2025-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2025/05/04/sabatic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2025/05/04/sabatic.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="what-happened-with-me-last-year">What happened with me last year?</h1>

<p>Since August 2024, I’ve been back in my hometown, Ocotlán de Morelos, in the state of Oaxaca. The main reason was that job opportunities had practically disappeared. On top of that, my girlfriend asked me to spend more time with her, and I thought it was a good moment to reconnect with my roots, my family, and everything I had left behind.</p>

<p>However, due to the poor infrastructure in the area — especially the low-quality internet service — the lack of hardware and tools for working with electronics, and most importantly, not having enough time, I haven’t been able to continue developing microcontroller projects.
Even so, I’m still working — very hard, in fact — because my grandmother needs my help with her farm.</p>

<p>If you want a summary of these past months, keep reading.</p>

<p>Last year, in July, I managed to buy a vehicle. I had been saving money for a while to afford one. Once I got the car, I returned to Oaxaca from Monterrey — a long journey of over 1,500 km, crossing almost three-quarters of the country.
After that trip, I arrived at my parents’ home and spent some time with them and my girlfriend.</p>

<h2 id="working-with-plants">Working with plants.</h2>
<p>Back in my old home, I tried to continue with the projects on this blog. However, the rainy season had just started, and after years of working without a proper mental break, I decided to step away from programming and technology for a while.
I took the opportunity to experiment with crops — both in a small grove my dad owns and on my grandma’s farm.</p>

<h3 id="results">Results</h3>
<p>The corn, chickpeas, and pumpkins on my grandma’s land turned out really well. I arrived just in time to help her and my cousin, from seeding all the way to harvest. I was so happy doing it, and my mind finally got the break it needed. I also spent more time with my girlfriend and reconnected with the experience of living through manual, hard work on the farm.</p>

<p>However, in Oaxaca, those products don’t have much real market value. And unfortunately, my family is hesitant to invest a proper amount of money to improve production or adopt better technology. That was frustrating because the results were good, and I saw real potential.</p>

<p>In a future update, I’ll share some pictures from the farm — if I remember.
I know this blog is about technology, microcontrollers, electronics, and programming… not farming or things like that.</p>

<p>Well, I started studying the Rust programming language and continued with C. It was really hard for me — not because of the technical complexity, but because of the slow internet, my girlfriend asking for more time, and my mom constantly calling me to help her.
I missed my own apartment… and being alone, haha.</p>

<h2 id="after-the-storm-comes-the-calm">After the storm comes the calm.</h2>
<p>Anyway, I returned to Monterrey last week. Now I need to find a job and get back to my electronics projects. 
I’m currently adapting OpenBLT for a Bluepill board, aiming to build a strong project by applying the skills and tools I’ve developed throughout my journey in embedded systems.</p>

<h2 id="to-be-honest-im-a-bit-worried">To be honest, I’m a bit worried.</h2>
<p>My savings are starting to run out, I still owe money on my car, and now that I’m living with my girlfriend, my expenses have increased. I’ve even considered looking for a job outside the embedded systems field. The companies that usually post relevant positions are publishing fewer openings, and when they do, I see at least fifty other applicants besides me.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="thinking" /><category term="farming" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What happened with me last year? Since August 2024, I’ve been back in my hometown, Ocotlán de Morelos, in the state of Oaxaca. The main reason was that job opportunities had practically disappeared. On top of that, my girlfriend asked me to spend more time with her, and I thought it was a good moment to reconnect with my roots, my family, and everything I had left behind. However, due to the poor infrastructure in the area — especially the low-quality internet service — the lack of hardware and tools for working with electronics, and most importantly, not having enough time, I haven’t been able to continue developing microcontroller projects. Even so, I’m still working — very hard, in fact — because my grandmother needs my help with her farm. If you want a summary of these past months, keep reading. Last year, in July, I managed to buy a vehicle. I had been saving money for a while to afford one. Once I got the car, I returned to Oaxaca from Monterrey — a long journey of over 1,500 km, crossing almost three-quarters of the country. After that trip, I arrived at my parents’ home and spent some time with them and my girlfriend. Working with plants. Back in my old home, I tried to continue with the projects on this blog. However, the rainy season had just started, and after years of working without a proper mental break, I decided to step away from programming and technology for a while. I took the opportunity to experiment with crops — both in a small grove my dad owns and on my grandma’s farm. Results The corn, chickpeas, and pumpkins on my grandma’s land turned out really well. I arrived just in time to help her and my cousin, from seeding all the way to harvest. I was so happy doing it, and my mind finally got the break it needed. I also spent more time with my girlfriend and reconnected with the experience of living through manual, hard work on the farm. However, in Oaxaca, those products don’t have much real market value. And unfortunately, my family is hesitant to invest a proper amount of money to improve production or adopt better technology. That was frustrating because the results were good, and I saw real potential. In a future update, I’ll share some pictures from the farm — if I remember. I know this blog is about technology, microcontrollers, electronics, and programming… not farming or things like that. Well, I started studying the Rust programming language and continued with C. It was really hard for me — not because of the technical complexity, but because of the slow internet, my girlfriend asking for more time, and my mom constantly calling me to help her. I missed my own apartment… and being alone, haha. After the storm comes the calm. Anyway, I returned to Monterrey last week. Now I need to find a job and get back to my electronics projects. I’m currently adapting OpenBLT for a Bluepill board, aiming to build a strong project by applying the skills and tools I’ve developed throughout my journey in embedded systems. To be honest, I’m a bit worried. My savings are starting to run out, I still owe money on my car, and now that I’m living with my girlfriend, my expenses have increased. I’ve even considered looking for a job outside the embedded systems field. The companies that usually post relevant positions are publishing fewer openings, and when they do, I see at least fifty other applicants besides me.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I am farmer now!</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/09/18/nowIamFarmer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I am farmer now!" /><published>2024-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/09/18/nowIamFarmer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/09/18/nowIamFarmer.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="i-have-been-disconnected-last-month">I have been disconnected last month</h2>

<p>Long story short, I’m still stuck in unemployment. After a lot of thinking, I decided to move to Oaxaca for a few months, though with low spirits and few expectations. I know there are far fewer job opportunities for me here, and even landing a remote position is quite complicated. However, it’s in tough times that opportunities often arise.</p>

<p>Since August, I’ve been with my family, spending quality time with my parents, my girlfriend, and my newborn niece. So far, so good. But, during one of those reflective moments, the idea of returning to my roots came to mind. My maternal grandparents have been farmers their whole lives. I used to spend the summers of my childhood happily at their farm, helping out however I could and they would let me.</p>

<p>My grandfather passed away almost eight years ago. He was working on his cornfields when he got sick and had to go to the hospital; unfortunately, he never returned alive. My grandmother, day by day, continues taking care of her cows and sheep, and with the help of my cousin, they maintain the land and the farm as best they can, given their strength and resources.</p>

<p>I’m filled with nostalgia for those Fridays when we would go eat with my grandparents, give water to the animals, clear weeds from the fields, cut alfalfa, harvest corn and squash, and clean beans during the harvest season…</p>

<p>This, along with the plans I had as a recent university graduate months before my grandfather passed away—when I dreamed of creating a farm with technology and automation—made me realize that the time had come. Instead of lamenting the fact that company X doesn’t want my programming services, I can swap the computer for a machete, an axe, a sickle, and a shovel to start building the foundations of what was once just a dream.</p>

<p>Here I am, convincing my grandmother to experiment with new crops, to automate some tasks on the farm to make it easier to manage, and to apply the technology I’ve learned over the years for the benefit of everyone in the family. So, new posts about what I’ve been doing lately are coming soon, along with a new section on the blog: The Farm.</p>

<h2 id="first-steps">First Steps</h2>

<p>The first thing I had to do was help clean one of my grandmother’s fields, already planted with seasonal corn. So, I had to pull weeds and fertilize the soil with urea. This took me two weeks with my dad’s help. Fortunately, this year it has rained enough to ensure a modest harvest, as the area has experienced several years of drought.</p>

<p>Since the family is dedicated to raising goats, sheep, cows, chickens, and turkeys, they have been cultivating forage and grains. In my opinion, we should experiment with other types of forage, different from alfalfa and corn. So, I will experiment with wheat, oats, and some other cereals that can be grown. I’ve always enjoyed growing vegetables like carrots, peppers, and spinach, so on a plot of land owned by my parents, I’ll experiment with other crops to present to my grandmother and see if they can be rotated with the main crop, which is corn.</p>

<p>Another project is to maintain the pens, feeders, and water troughs for the animals, to ensure the livestock is in better conditions.</p>

<p>Lastly, I’ve been doing some research and just made an organic insecticide based on chili peppers.</p>

<p>I will be posting results in the new section.
<em>*This translation uses chat GPT to correct my translation</em></p>

<h1 id="spanish">Spanish</h1>
<h2 id="ahora-seré-granjero">Ahora seré granjero</h2>

<p>Estuve desconectado el último mes (o los últimos dos, ya ni lo recuerdo). Historia corta, sigo en las garras del desempleo. Después de mucho pensar, decidí mudarme por unos meses a Oaxaca, aunque con pocas expectativas y sin muchos ánimos. Sé que hay muchas menos oportunidades laborales para mí, y que incluso conseguir un puesto remoto es bastante complicado. Sin embargo, es en los malos momentos cuando surgen las oportunidades.</p>

<p>Desde agosto he estado con mi familia, disfrutando tiempo de calidad con mis padres, mi novia y una sobrinita que acaba de nacer. Todo bien hasta ahí. Pero, en uno de esos momentos de reflexión, se me ocurrió la idea de volver a mis raíces. Mis abuelos maternos han sido agricultores toda la vida. Los veranos de mi infancia los pasaba felizmente en su casa/granja, ayudando en lo que podía y me dejaban.</p>

<p>Mi abuelo falleció hace casi ocho años. Estaba trabajando en sus terrenos de maíz cuando enfermó y tuvo que ir al hospital; lamentablemente, no regresó con vida. Mi abuela, día a día, sigue cuidando de sus vacas y borregos, y junto con la ayuda de mi primo, mantienen las tierras y la granja dentro de sus posibilidades y fuerzas.</p>

<p>Me invade la nostalgia de esos viernes en los que íbamos a comer con mis abuelos, de darles agua a los animales, de limpiar de maleza los terrenos de siembra, cortar alfalfa, cosechar maíz, calabaza y limpiar los frijoles en la temporada de cosecha…</p>

<p>Esto, sumado a los planes que tenía como recién egresado de la universidad meses antes de que falleciera mi abuelo, cuando soñaba con hacer una granja con tecnología y automatización… Me dije a mí mismo: ha llegado el día. En lugar de lamentarme porque <strong>X</strong> empresa no quiere mis servicios de programación, puedo cambiar la computadora por un machete, un hacha, una hoz y una pala, para comenzar a construir las bases de lo que un día solo fue un sueño.</p>

<p>Aquí estoy, convenciendo a mi abuela de experimentar con nuevos cultivos, de automatizar algunas tareas en la granja para facilitar su manejo, y de aplicar la tecnología que he aprendido en estos años para el beneficio de todos en la familia. Así que pronto vendrán publicaciones sobre lo que he estado haciendo últimamente y una nueva sección en el blog: <strong>The Farm</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="primeros-pasos">Primeros pasos</h2>

<p>Lo primero que me tocó hacer fue ayudar con la limpieza de uno de los terrenos de la abuela, ya sembrado con maíz de temporal. Así que tocó arrancar malezas y fertilizar el suelo con urea. Esto me llevó dos semanas con la ayuda de mi papá. Afortunadamente, este año ha llovido lo suficiente para garantizar una cosecha modesta, porque en la zona se han vivido varios años de sequía.</p>

<p>Dado que la familia se dedica a la cría de chivos, borregos, vacas, gallinas y guajolotes, han estado cultivando forraje y granos. En mi opinión, deberíamos experimentar con otro tipo de forraje, distinto a la alfalfa y el maíz. Así que experimentaré con trigo, avena y algún otro cereal que se pueda cultivar. Siempre me ha gustado cultivar hortalizas como zanahorias, chiles y espinacas, así que en un terreno que es propiedad de mis padres haré experimentos con otros cultivos para presentarlos a mi abuela y ver si se pueden rotar con el principal cultivo, que es el maíz.</p>

<p>Otro proyecto es dar mantenimiento a los corrales, comederos y bebederos de los animales, para que el ganado esté en mejores condiciones.</p>

<p>Por último, he estado investigando y acabo de hacer un insecticida orgánico a base de chiles.</p>

<p>Iré publicando resultados en la nueva sección.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="Farming" /><category term="Blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been disconnected last month Long story short, I’m still stuck in unemployment. After a lot of thinking, I decided to move to Oaxaca for a few months, though with low spirits and few expectations. I know there are far fewer job opportunities for me here, and even landing a remote position is quite complicated. However, it’s in tough times that opportunities often arise. Since August, I’ve been with my family, spending quality time with my parents, my girlfriend, and my newborn niece. So far, so good. But, during one of those reflective moments, the idea of returning to my roots came to mind. My maternal grandparents have been farmers their whole lives. I used to spend the summers of my childhood happily at their farm, helping out however I could and they would let me. My grandfather passed away almost eight years ago. He was working on his cornfields when he got sick and had to go to the hospital; unfortunately, he never returned alive. My grandmother, day by day, continues taking care of her cows and sheep, and with the help of my cousin, they maintain the land and the farm as best they can, given their strength and resources. I’m filled with nostalgia for those Fridays when we would go eat with my grandparents, give water to the animals, clear weeds from the fields, cut alfalfa, harvest corn and squash, and clean beans during the harvest season… This, along with the plans I had as a recent university graduate months before my grandfather passed away—when I dreamed of creating a farm with technology and automation—made me realize that the time had come. Instead of lamenting the fact that company X doesn’t want my programming services, I can swap the computer for a machete, an axe, a sickle, and a shovel to start building the foundations of what was once just a dream. Here I am, convincing my grandmother to experiment with new crops, to automate some tasks on the farm to make it easier to manage, and to apply the technology I’ve learned over the years for the benefit of everyone in the family. So, new posts about what I’ve been doing lately are coming soon, along with a new section on the blog: The Farm. First Steps The first thing I had to do was help clean one of my grandmother’s fields, already planted with seasonal corn. So, I had to pull weeds and fertilize the soil with urea. This took me two weeks with my dad’s help. Fortunately, this year it has rained enough to ensure a modest harvest, as the area has experienced several years of drought. Since the family is dedicated to raising goats, sheep, cows, chickens, and turkeys, they have been cultivating forage and grains. In my opinion, we should experiment with other types of forage, different from alfalfa and corn. So, I will experiment with wheat, oats, and some other cereals that can be grown. I’ve always enjoyed growing vegetables like carrots, peppers, and spinach, so on a plot of land owned by my parents, I’ll experiment with other crops to present to my grandmother and see if they can be rotated with the main crop, which is corn. Another project is to maintain the pens, feeders, and water troughs for the animals, to ensure the livestock is in better conditions. Lastly, I’ve been doing some research and just made an organic insecticide based on chili peppers. I will be posting results in the new section. *This translation uses chat GPT to correct my translation Spanish Ahora seré granjero Estuve desconectado el último mes (o los últimos dos, ya ni lo recuerdo). Historia corta, sigo en las garras del desempleo. Después de mucho pensar, decidí mudarme por unos meses a Oaxaca, aunque con pocas expectativas y sin muchos ánimos. Sé que hay muchas menos oportunidades laborales para mí, y que incluso conseguir un puesto remoto es bastante complicado. Sin embargo, es en los malos momentos cuando surgen las oportunidades. Desde agosto he estado con mi familia, disfrutando tiempo de calidad con mis padres, mi novia y una sobrinita que acaba de nacer. Todo bien hasta ahí. Pero, en uno de esos momentos de reflexión, se me ocurrió la idea de volver a mis raíces. Mis abuelos maternos han sido agricultores toda la vida. Los veranos de mi infancia los pasaba felizmente en su casa/granja, ayudando en lo que podía y me dejaban. Mi abuelo falleció hace casi ocho años. Estaba trabajando en sus terrenos de maíz cuando enfermó y tuvo que ir al hospital; lamentablemente, no regresó con vida. Mi abuela, día a día, sigue cuidando de sus vacas y borregos, y junto con la ayuda de mi primo, mantienen las tierras y la granja dentro de sus posibilidades y fuerzas. Me invade la nostalgia de esos viernes en los que íbamos a comer con mis abuelos, de darles agua a los animales, de limpiar de maleza los terrenos de siembra, cortar alfalfa, cosechar maíz, calabaza y limpiar los frijoles en la temporada de cosecha… Esto, sumado a los planes que tenía como recién egresado de la universidad meses antes de que falleciera mi abuelo, cuando soñaba con hacer una granja con tecnología y automatización… Me dije a mí mismo: ha llegado el día. En lugar de lamentarme porque X empresa no quiere mis servicios de programación, puedo cambiar la computadora por un machete, un hacha, una hoz y una pala, para comenzar a construir las bases de lo que un día solo fue un sueño. Aquí estoy, convenciendo a mi abuela de experimentar con nuevos cultivos, de automatizar algunas tareas en la granja para facilitar su manejo, y de aplicar la tecnología que he aprendido en estos años para el beneficio de todos en la familia. Así que pronto vendrán publicaciones sobre lo que he estado haciendo últimamente y una nueva sección en el blog: The Farm. Primeros pasos Lo primero que me tocó hacer fue ayudar con la limpieza de uno de los terrenos de la abuela, ya sembrado con maíz de temporal. Así que tocó arrancar malezas y fertilizar el suelo con urea. Esto me llevó dos semanas con la ayuda de mi papá. Afortunadamente, este año ha llovido lo suficiente para garantizar una cosecha modesta, porque en la zona se han vivido varios años de sequía. Dado que la familia se dedica a la cría de chivos, borregos, vacas, gallinas y guajolotes, han estado cultivando forraje y granos. En mi opinión, deberíamos experimentar con otro tipo de forraje, distinto a la alfalfa y el maíz. Así que experimentaré con trigo, avena y algún otro cereal que se pueda cultivar. Siempre me ha gustado cultivar hortalizas como zanahorias, chiles y espinacas, así que en un terreno que es propiedad de mis padres haré experimentos con otros cultivos para presentarlos a mi abuela y ver si se pueden rotar con el principal cultivo, que es el maíz. Otro proyecto es dar mantenimiento a los corrales, comederos y bebederos de los animales, para que el ganado esté en mejores condiciones. Por último, he estado investigando y acabo de hacer un insecticida orgánico a base de chiles. Iré publicando resultados en la nueva sección.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AVR project</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/07/13/avr-project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AVR project" /><published>2024-07-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/07/13/avr-project</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/07/13/avr-project.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="july-10">July 10</h2>
<p>The last few weeks, I had a lot of troubles with my <strong>3D printer</strong>, and I left my C++ course. The reasons: I don’t have enough experience with the 3D printer, and I made some mistakes that affected its functionality. For example, the nozzle became useless after the filament was affected by humidity and temperature. I also had troubles with the <strong>M4V6 Hotend</strong> Kit and damaged the <strong>PTFE</strong> tube when I tried to remove it. Additionally, there was a bad calibration of the <strong>Printer Hotbed</strong>.
After ordering a packet of nozzles, replacing the hotbed with a glass panel, and recalibrating the machine, the printer is working again.</p>

<h2 id="july-14">July 14</h2>

<p>I was thinking of doing a project with an STM32F microcontroller. However, I had an ATMEGA328p that I hadn’t used, along with wires, a breadboard, ASP programer and a lot of new components I bought years ago. My injured pride from never developing with AVR microcontrollers in a Linux environment also weighed on my mind.</p>

<p>This situation bothered me, so I decided to use it as therapy and create a basic manual for developing with 8-bit microcontrollers using Linux. <br />
Well, the results will be published on this site.</p>

<h2 id="july-15">July 15</h2>

<p>Finally, I was able to build a project and flash an <strong>ATMEGA328p</strong> with <strong>avrdude</strong>. It is a simple sequence to turn on and off the components in an RGB LED using a simple state machine implemented with a structure. I will explain it in a post. I believe it’s a good introduction to embedded software development using free tools. <br />
The challenge was the hardware; I am very out of practice with it.</p>

<h2 id="july-17">July 17</h2>

<p>X - Files is a very good show finally I am watching the season 10 and 11 I don’t believe that I lost the interest in that things!</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="thinking" /><category term="AVR" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[July 10 The last few weeks, I had a lot of troubles with my 3D printer, and I left my C++ course. The reasons: I don’t have enough experience with the 3D printer, and I made some mistakes that affected its functionality. For example, the nozzle became useless after the filament was affected by humidity and temperature. I also had troubles with the M4V6 Hotend Kit and damaged the PTFE tube when I tried to remove it. Additionally, there was a bad calibration of the Printer Hotbed. After ordering a packet of nozzles, replacing the hotbed with a glass panel, and recalibrating the machine, the printer is working again. July 14 I was thinking of doing a project with an STM32F microcontroller. However, I had an ATMEGA328p that I hadn’t used, along with wires, a breadboard, ASP programer and a lot of new components I bought years ago. My injured pride from never developing with AVR microcontrollers in a Linux environment also weighed on my mind. This situation bothered me, so I decided to use it as therapy and create a basic manual for developing with 8-bit microcontrollers using Linux. Well, the results will be published on this site. July 15 Finally, I was able to build a project and flash an ATMEGA328p with avrdude. It is a simple sequence to turn on and off the components in an RGB LED using a simple state machine implemented with a structure. I will explain it in a post. I believe it’s a good introduction to embedded software development using free tools. The challenge was the hardware; I am very out of practice with it. July 17 X - Files is a very good show finally I am watching the season 10 and 11 I don’t believe that I lost the interest in that things!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I am blocked!</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/06/22/block01.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I am blocked!" /><published>2024-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/06/22/block01</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/06/22/block01.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="june-15">June 15</h2>
<p>I recently started a C++ course because I know the concepts of Object-Oriented Programming. However, it is a bit difficult for me. Some topics are easy, and I get tired quickly, but the new concepts take time to learn. It is a contradiction, I think, but I am making a big effort to be disciplined and learn everything quickly and well.</p>

<h2 id="june-18">June 18</h2>
<p>I am recording a couple of videos to upload to YouTube. It is a significant challenge for me because I don’t like taking pictures or videos. It is very uncomfortable for me, as an old-school nerd who grew up in internet forums like Taringa, bak.com, and using resources like Encarta and Wikipedia.
I was tired of the C++ course, but I need to create another source of income because I don’t have a formal job and am living off my investments and savings.</p>

<h2 id="june-20">June 20</h2>
<p>I post a couple of videos in youeube related to fix the Zonestar Z8p control encoder and how to soldering pins of a black phill board from WeAct.</p>

<h2 id="june-21">June 21</h2>
<p>The Udemy courses are good, but I get bored after a couple of hours. I am tired, but I need discipline.</p>

<h2 id="june-22">June 22</h2>
<p>Well, I am advancing with my course, but the boredom was killing me. I procrastinated for a couple of hours, but a thought started to circle in my mind. Can I compile a C/C++ AVR project in Linux? I hadn’t done it without Atmel Studio (the last project I did was before Microchip bought Atmel). After reading some posts, watching a few videos, and checking the plugins in Visual Studio Code, I found the answer… I can do it, and I did it! It only cost me 4 hours of my life, haha.  <br />
Right now, it’s 4:00 am. I’m going to sleep.</p>

<p>Well it is 6pm I will start to do my C++ course…</p>
<h2 id="june-23">June 23</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Nothing wrong with me!</li>
  <li>Nothing wrong with me!</li>
  <li>…</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="blog" /><category term="thinking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[June 15 I recently started a C++ course because I know the concepts of Object-Oriented Programming. However, it is a bit difficult for me. Some topics are easy, and I get tired quickly, but the new concepts take time to learn. It is a contradiction, I think, but I am making a big effort to be disciplined and learn everything quickly and well. June 18 I am recording a couple of videos to upload to YouTube. It is a significant challenge for me because I don’t like taking pictures or videos. It is very uncomfortable for me, as an old-school nerd who grew up in internet forums like Taringa, bak.com, and using resources like Encarta and Wikipedia. I was tired of the C++ course, but I need to create another source of income because I don’t have a formal job and am living off my investments and savings. June 20 I post a couple of videos in youeube related to fix the Zonestar Z8p control encoder and how to soldering pins of a black phill board from WeAct. June 21 The Udemy courses are good, but I get bored after a couple of hours. I am tired, but I need discipline. June 22 Well, I am advancing with my course, but the boredom was killing me. I procrastinated for a couple of hours, but a thought started to circle in my mind. Can I compile a C/C++ AVR project in Linux? I hadn’t done it without Atmel Studio (the last project I did was before Microchip bought Atmel). After reading some posts, watching a few videos, and checking the plugins in Visual Studio Code, I found the answer… I can do it, and I did it! It only cost me 4 hours of my life, haha. Right now, it’s 4:00 am. I’m going to sleep. Well it is 6pm I will start to do my C++ course… June 23 Nothing wrong with me! Nothing wrong with me! …]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Openblt to STM Nucleo-64</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/15/star-with-openblt-project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Openblt to STM Nucleo-64" /><published>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/15/star-with-openblt-project</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/15/star-with-openblt-project.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="april-15-24">April-15-24</h3>
<h1 id="starting-the-implementation-of-openblt-project">Starting the Implementation of OpenBlt Project</h1>
<p>I am beginning work on implementing the OpenBLT project on a Nucleo 64 platform with an <strong>STM32-F446RE</strong> microcontroller.</p>

<p>In my previous job, I implemented this project for a <strong>STM34H53</strong> platform. At that time, I didn’t have enough time to fully understand how the software works. I modified the sources to work with CAN bus for a demo, and then another task was assigned to me. However, I believe that OpenBLT has more potential, and I will need to use it for my projects in the future.</p>

<h3 id="april-17-24">April-17-24</h3>
<h2 id="read-documentation">Read Documentation</h2>
<p>I was reading  the <a href="https://www.feaser.com/en">OpenBLT</a> site and checking the <a href="https://www.feaser.com/openblt/doku.php?id=download">download</a>,  <a href="https://www.feaser.com/en/blog/">Developer Blog</a>, and <a href="https://www.feaser.com/openblt/doku.php">wiki</a> sections. I noticed that <strong>Nucleo-F446RE</strong> board have a demo with Modbus RTU, I didn’t know what it was, so I researched some information.
Once I learned that Modbus RTU is a serial or Ethernet communication protocol based on master/slave architecture, I will try to set it up or modify it to flash applications with at least CAN. If I have time enough I’ll try to run another interface for example RS232 or USB.</p>

<h1 id="working-with-a-custom-openblt">Working with a custom OpenBLT</h1>
<h3 id="may-04-24">May-04-24</h3>
<p>Recently, I have been studying the architecture of the <strong>OpenBLT</strong> project, and I noticed that it is simple to understand, although it has a good structure and is very complete in resource administration, such as <strong>CAN</strong> and <strong>RS232</strong>. The first steps to add features will be to enable the functions of USART to use a TTL converter to flash an application.</p>

<h3 id="may-10-24">May-10-24</h3>
<p>I publish in this blog <a href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/projects/en/1-openblt/openblt-start">how to import</a> the project to STM32Cube IDE software, This is a tool provided by STM to use the protocol</p>

<h3 id="may-14-24">May-14-24</h3>
<p>The project is taking longer than I expected. I understand how the resources work, I configured the system, GPIOs, timers, and it still doesn’t work. Nevertheless, I am still trying. I am sure that the problem is a minor issue related to my own lack of knowledge.</p>

<h3 id="may-17-24">May-17-24</h3>
<p>Finally, I managed to enable RS232. I had some trouble with the connection because I accidentally defined ports twice. Also, I was trying to flash using the USB-TTL in a resource that is part of a virtual COM embedded with the STLink port. Oh well, now my focus is on setting up CAN.</p>

<h3 id="may-20-24">May-20-24</h3>
<p>While researching an example of CAN bus functionality for the Nucleo-F446RE, I found <a href="https://controllerstech.com/can-protocol-in-stm32/">Controllerstech</a> tuturial. It was so useful in helping me understand how to manage resources and enable CAN in my custom OpenBLT project.</p>

<p>I spent a lot of time on this challenge because the STM HAL CAN driver needed to be integrated into the project. My first obstacle was that <strong>CAN</strong> didn’t work. I wrote a test code to run only the configuration and transmission of a loop message to check if the baud rate was correctly enabled, but to my surprise, it did nothing. After a good amount of debugging time with <strong>ST-Link</strong>, I noticed that the functions <strong>HAL_CAN_Init()</strong> and <strong>HAL_CAN_Start</strong> didn’t work normally because a timer value was not updated by the <strong>HAL_GetTick()</strong> function.</p>

<p>Upon investigating why this happened, I found that <strong>HAL_GetTick()</strong> was defined in <strong>timer.h</strong> and also in <strong>stm32f4xx_hal.h</strong>. I solved this issue by renaming the function to <strong>HAL_GetTick_openblt</strong> in all files of the OpenBLT layer.</p>

<p><em>In Mexico, May 20 is the <strong>Psychologist Day</strong>, and my girlfriend is a psychologist. I forgot about it while dealing with the issue in the CAN bus.</em> Sometimes I wish I weren’t so obsessive. If someday you read these lines, Honey, forgive me. I swear that I love you. But an engineer lost his ground debugging.</p>

<h3 id="may-21-24">May-21-24</h3>
<p>While taking snapshots for the documentation, I noticed that if the <strong>CAN interface is enable but not connected, the bootloader never starts</strong>. This is because, in the initialization routine, it needs to be connected to a CAN bus. If you encounter this issue and don’t want to connect a transceiver, <strong>you can cross the pins CAN_Tx and CAN_Rx</strong> to initialize the bootloader. This trick can help rule out software issues. I hope this saves you some time.</p>

<h3 id="may-22-24">May-22-24</h3>
<h1 id="challenge-complete">Challenge complete!</h1>
<p>Finally the system is working and the documentation is done. 
If you come here loking for a solution, Enjoy it!
You can see the process here: <a href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/projects/en/1-openblt/open-blt">OpenBLT in Nucleo-F446RE</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="projects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[April-15-24 Starting the Implementation of OpenBlt Project I am beginning work on implementing the OpenBLT project on a Nucleo 64 platform with an STM32-F446RE microcontroller. In my previous job, I implemented this project for a STM34H53 platform. At that time, I didn’t have enough time to fully understand how the software works. I modified the sources to work with CAN bus for a demo, and then another task was assigned to me. However, I believe that OpenBLT has more potential, and I will need to use it for my projects in the future. April-17-24 Read Documentation I was reading the OpenBLT site and checking the download, Developer Blog, and wiki sections. I noticed that Nucleo-F446RE board have a demo with Modbus RTU, I didn’t know what it was, so I researched some information. Once I learned that Modbus RTU is a serial or Ethernet communication protocol based on master/slave architecture, I will try to set it up or modify it to flash applications with at least CAN. If I have time enough I’ll try to run another interface for example RS232 or USB. Working with a custom OpenBLT May-04-24 Recently, I have been studying the architecture of the OpenBLT project, and I noticed that it is simple to understand, although it has a good structure and is very complete in resource administration, such as CAN and RS232. The first steps to add features will be to enable the functions of USART to use a TTL converter to flash an application. May-10-24 I publish in this blog how to import the project to STM32Cube IDE software, This is a tool provided by STM to use the protocol May-14-24 The project is taking longer than I expected. I understand how the resources work, I configured the system, GPIOs, timers, and it still doesn’t work. Nevertheless, I am still trying. I am sure that the problem is a minor issue related to my own lack of knowledge. May-17-24 Finally, I managed to enable RS232. I had some trouble with the connection because I accidentally defined ports twice. Also, I was trying to flash using the USB-TTL in a resource that is part of a virtual COM embedded with the STLink port. Oh well, now my focus is on setting up CAN. May-20-24 While researching an example of CAN bus functionality for the Nucleo-F446RE, I found Controllerstech tuturial. It was so useful in helping me understand how to manage resources and enable CAN in my custom OpenBLT project. I spent a lot of time on this challenge because the STM HAL CAN driver needed to be integrated into the project. My first obstacle was that CAN didn’t work. I wrote a test code to run only the configuration and transmission of a loop message to check if the baud rate was correctly enabled, but to my surprise, it did nothing. After a good amount of debugging time with ST-Link, I noticed that the functions HAL_CAN_Init() and HAL_CAN_Start didn’t work normally because a timer value was not updated by the HAL_GetTick() function. Upon investigating why this happened, I found that HAL_GetTick() was defined in timer.h and also in stm32f4xx_hal.h. I solved this issue by renaming the function to HAL_GetTick_openblt in all files of the OpenBLT layer. In Mexico, May 20 is the Psychologist Day, and my girlfriend is a psychologist. I forgot about it while dealing with the issue in the CAN bus. Sometimes I wish I weren’t so obsessive. If someday you read these lines, Honey, forgive me. I swear that I love you. But an engineer lost his ground debugging. May-21-24 While taking snapshots for the documentation, I noticed that if the CAN interface is enable but not connected, the bootloader never starts. This is because, in the initialization routine, it needs to be connected to a CAN bus. If you encounter this issue and don’t want to connect a transceiver, you can cross the pins CAN_Tx and CAN_Rx to initialize the bootloader. This trick can help rule out software issues. I hope this saves you some time. May-22-24 Challenge complete! Finally the system is working and the documentation is done. If you come here loking for a solution, Enjoy it! You can see the process here: OpenBLT in Nucleo-F446RE.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">After vacations!</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/14/after-vacations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="After vacations!" /><published>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/14/after-vacations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/14/after-vacations.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="after-vacations">After vacations</h2>
<p>After a busy work season, a break is necessary.
“Last week of February, I wanted to take a couple of days off, and I managed to get it for an indefinite period.” - Abner, my brother.
We worked as embedded software developers in the same company for a while, and unfortunately, the layoffs in high technology companies affected us.</p>

<p>I was exhausted from programming because last month at work, I had to work more than 10 hours a day just to learn how to do my tasks. However, I was laid off from my job. After these canon events I decide do some Udemy curses, pick up ciclysm again to  prepare myself phisically and mentally for a new season.</p>

<p>I took a Scrum course focused on Jira to improve these skills.
During the last week of March and the first week of April, I took a break to disconnect from computers and work.
Yesterday, I finished a course to enhance my knowledge of the Yocto Project.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After vacations After a busy work season, a break is necessary. “Last week of February, I wanted to take a couple of days off, and I managed to get it for an indefinite period.” - Abner, my brother. We worked as embedded software developers in the same company for a while, and unfortunately, the layoffs in high technology companies affected us. I was exhausted from programming because last month at work, I had to work more than 10 hours a day just to learn how to do my tasks. However, I was laid off from my job. After these canon events I decide do some Udemy curses, pick up ciclysm again to prepare myself phisically and mentally for a new season. I took a Scrum course focused on Jira to improve these skills. During the last week of March and the first week of April, I took a break to disconnect from computers and work. Yesterday, I finished a course to enhance my knowledge of the Yocto Project.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to the jungle!</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/03/16/first-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to the jungle!" /><published>2024-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/03/16/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/03/16/first-post.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="this-is-my-first-post-to-this-blog">This is my first post to this blog.</h2>

<p>These posts will be the record of the time and troubles that I encounter when I work on a project.
You can get an idea of the duration and complexity of the project before or until you do something related.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is my first post to this blog. These posts will be the record of the time and troubles that I encounter when I work on a project. You can get an idea of the duration and complexity of the project before or until you do something related.]]></summary></entry></feed>