<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-04-15T03:53:26+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rising Embedded Mx</title><subtitle>This is my world, where I can do what I think
</subtitle><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Openblt to STM Nucleo-64</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/15/star-with-openblt-project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Openblt to STM Nucleo-64" /><published>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/15/star-with-openblt-project</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/15/star-with-openblt-project.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="starting-the-implementation-of-openblt-project">Starting the Implementation of OpenBlt Project</h2>

<p>Today, I am beginning work on implementing the OpenBlt project. In my previous job, I implemented this project for an <strong>STM34H53</strong> platform. However, I will now port the project to a Nucleo 64 platform with an <strong>STM32F446</strong> microcontroller.</p>

<p>I don’t believe that it’s an easy task, but as engineers, we thrive on challenges, and <strong>‘impossible’ is what we do</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="projects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Starting the Implementation of OpenBlt Project Today, I am beginning work on implementing the OpenBlt project. In my previous job, I implemented this project for an STM34H53 platform. However, I will now port the project to a Nucleo 64 platform with an STM32F446 microcontroller. I don’t believe that it’s an easy task, but as engineers, we thrive on challenges, and ‘impossible’ is what we do.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">After vacations!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/14/after-vacations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="After vacations!" /><published>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/14/after-vacations</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/14/after-vacations.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="after-vacations">After vacations</h2>
<p>After a busy work season, a break is necessary.
“Last week of February, I wanted to take a couple of days off, and I managed to get it for an indefinite period.” - Abner, my brother.
We worked as embedded software developers in the same company for a while, and unfortunately, the layoffs in high technology companies affected us.</p>

<p>I was exhausted from programming because last month at work, I had to work more than 10 hours a day just to learn how to do my tasks. However, I was laid off from my job. After these canon events I decide do some Udemy curses, pick up ciclysm again to  prepare myself phisically and mentally for a new season.</p>

<p>I took a Scrum course focused on Jira to improve these skills.
During the last week of March and the first week of April, I took a break to disconnect from computers and work.
Yesterday, I finished a course to enhance my knowledge of the Yocto Project.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After vacations After a busy work season, a break is necessary. “Last week of February, I wanted to take a couple of days off, and I managed to get it for an indefinite period.” - Abner, my brother. We worked as embedded software developers in the same company for a while, and unfortunately, the layoffs in high technology companies affected us. I was exhausted from programming because last month at work, I had to work more than 10 hours a day just to learn how to do my tasks. However, I was laid off from my job. After these canon events I decide do some Udemy curses, pick up ciclysm again to prepare myself phisically and mentally for a new season. I took a Scrum course focused on Jira to improve these skills. During the last week of March and the first week of April, I took a break to disconnect from computers and work. Yesterday, I finished a course to enhance my knowledge of the Yocto Project.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to the jungle!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/03/16/first-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to the jungle!" /><published>2024-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/03/16/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/03/16/first-post.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="this-is-my-first-post-to-this-blog">This is my first post to this blog.</h2>

<p>These posts will be the record of the time and troubles that I encounter when I work on a project.
You can get an idea of the duration and complexity of the project before or until you do something related.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is my first post to this blog. These posts will be the record of the time and troubles that I encounter when I work on a project. You can get an idea of the duration and complexity of the project before or until you do something related.]]></summary></entry></feed>