<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-05-28T03:24:50+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rising Embedded Mx</title><subtitle>This is my world, where I can do what I think
</subtitle><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Openblt to STM Nucleo-64</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/15/star-with-openblt-project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Openblt to STM Nucleo-64" /><published>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/15/star-with-openblt-project</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/15/star-with-openblt-project.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="april-15-24">April-15-24</h3>
<h1 id="starting-the-implementation-of-openblt-project">Starting the Implementation of OpenBlt Project</h1>
<p>I am beginning work on implementing the OpenBLT project on a Nucleo 64 platform with an <strong>STM32-F446RE</strong> microcontroller.</p>

<p>In my previous job, I implemented this project for a <strong>STM34H53</strong> platform. At that time, I didn’t have enough time to fully understand how the software works. I modified the sources to work with CAN bus for a demo, and then another task was assigned to me. However, I believe that OpenBLT has more potential, and I will need to use it for my projects in the future.</p>

<h3 id="april-17-24">April-17-24</h3>
<h2 id="read-documentation">Read Documentation</h2>
<p>I was reading  the <a href="https://www.feaser.com/en">OpenBLT</a> site and checking the <a href="https://www.feaser.com/openblt/doku.php?id=download">download</a>,  <a href="https://www.feaser.com/en/blog/">Developer Blog</a>, and <a href="https://www.feaser.com/openblt/doku.php">wiki</a> sections. I noticed that <strong>Nucleo-F446RE</strong> board have a demo with Modbus RTU, I didn’t know what it was, so I researched some information.
Once I learned that Modbus RTU is a serial or Ethernet communication protocol based on master/slave architecture, I will try to set it up or modify it to flash applications with at least CAN. If I have time enough I’ll try to run another interface for example RS232 or USB.</p>

<h1 id="working-with-a-custom-openblt">Working with a custom OpenBLT</h1>
<h3 id="may-04-24">May-04-24</h3>
<p>Recently, I have been studying the architecture of the <strong>OpenBLT</strong> project, and I noticed that it is simple to understand, although it has a good structure and is very complete in resource administration, such as <strong>CAN</strong> and <strong>RS232</strong>. The first steps to add features will be to enable the functions of USART to use a TTL converter to flash an application.</p>

<h3 id="may-10-24">May-10-24</h3>
<p>I publish in this blog <a href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/projects/en/openblt-start">how to import</a> the project to STM32Cube IDE software, This is a tool provided by STM to use the protocol</p>

<h3 id="may-14-24">May-14-24</h3>
<p>The project is taking longer than I expected. I understand how the resources work, I configured the system, GPIOs, timers, and it still doesn’t work. Nevertheless, I am still trying. I am sure that the problem is a minor issue related to my own lack of knowledge.</p>

<h3 id="may-17-24">May-17-24</h3>
<p>Finally, I managed to enable RS232. I had some trouble with the connection because I accidentally defined ports twice. Also, I was trying to flash using the USB-TTL in a resource that is part of a virtual COM embedded with the STLink port. Oh well, now my focus is on setting up CAN.</p>

<h3 id="may-20-24">May-20-24</h3>
<p>While researching an example of CAN bus functionality for the Nucleo-F446RE, I found <a href="https://controllerstech.com/can-protocol-in-stm32/">Controllerstech</a> tuturial. It was so useful in helping me understand how to manage resources and enable CAN in my custom OpenBLT project.</p>

<p>I spent a lot of time on this challenge because the STM HAL CAN driver needed to be integrated into the project. My first obstacle was that <strong>CAN</strong> didn’t work. I wrote a test code to run only the configuration and transmission of a loop message to check if the baud rate was correctly enabled, but to my surprise, it did nothing. After a good amount of debugging time with <strong>ST-Link</strong>, I noticed that the functions <strong>HAL_CAN_Init()</strong> and <strong>HAL_CAN_Start</strong> didn’t work normally because a timer value was not updated by the <strong>HAL_GetTick()</strong> function.</p>

<p>Upon investigating why this happened, I found that <strong>HAL_GetTick()</strong> was defined in <strong>timer.h</strong> and also in <strong>stm32f4xx_hal.h</strong>. I solved this issue by renaming the function to <strong>HAL_GetTick_openblt</strong> in all files of the OpenBLT layer.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In Mexico, May 20 is the Psychologist Day, and my girlfriend is a psychologist. I forgot about it while dealing with the issue in the CAN bus. Sometimes I wish I weren’t so obsessive. If someday you read these lines, Honey, forgive me. I swear that I love you. But an engineer lost his ground debugging.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="may-21-24">May-21-24</h3>
<p>While taking snapshots for the documentation, I noticed that if the <strong>CAN interface is enable but not connected, the bootloader never starts</strong>. This is because, in the initialization routine, it needs to be connected to a CAN bus. If you encounter this issue and don’t want to connect a transceiver, <strong>you can cross the pins CAN_Tx and CAN_Rx</strong> to initialize the bootloader. This trick can help rule out software issues. I hope this saves you some time.</p>

<h3 id="may-22-24">May-22-24</h3>
<h1 id="challenge-complete">Challenge complete!</h1>
<p>Finally the system is working and the documentation is done. 
If you come here loking for a solution, Enjoy it!
You can see the process here: <a href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/projects/en/open-blt">OpenBLT in Nucleo-F446RE</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="projects" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[April-15-24 Starting the Implementation of OpenBlt Project I am beginning work on implementing the OpenBLT project on a Nucleo 64 platform with an STM32-F446RE microcontroller. In my previous job, I implemented this project for a STM34H53 platform. At that time, I didn’t have enough time to fully understand how the software works. I modified the sources to work with CAN bus for a demo, and then another task was assigned to me. However, I believe that OpenBLT has more potential, and I will need to use it for my projects in the future. April-17-24 Read Documentation I was reading the OpenBLT site and checking the download, Developer Blog, and wiki sections. I noticed that Nucleo-F446RE board have a demo with Modbus RTU, I didn’t know what it was, so I researched some information. Once I learned that Modbus RTU is a serial or Ethernet communication protocol based on master/slave architecture, I will try to set it up or modify it to flash applications with at least CAN. If I have time enough I’ll try to run another interface for example RS232 or USB. Working with a custom OpenBLT May-04-24 Recently, I have been studying the architecture of the OpenBLT project, and I noticed that it is simple to understand, although it has a good structure and is very complete in resource administration, such as CAN and RS232. The first steps to add features will be to enable the functions of USART to use a TTL converter to flash an application. May-10-24 I publish in this blog how to import the project to STM32Cube IDE software, This is a tool provided by STM to use the protocol May-14-24 The project is taking longer than I expected. I understand how the resources work, I configured the system, GPIOs, timers, and it still doesn’t work. Nevertheless, I am still trying. I am sure that the problem is a minor issue related to my own lack of knowledge. May-17-24 Finally, I managed to enable RS232. I had some trouble with the connection because I accidentally defined ports twice. Also, I was trying to flash using the USB-TTL in a resource that is part of a virtual COM embedded with the STLink port. Oh well, now my focus is on setting up CAN. May-20-24 While researching an example of CAN bus functionality for the Nucleo-F446RE, I found Controllerstech tuturial. It was so useful in helping me understand how to manage resources and enable CAN in my custom OpenBLT project. I spent a lot of time on this challenge because the STM HAL CAN driver needed to be integrated into the project. My first obstacle was that CAN didn’t work. I wrote a test code to run only the configuration and transmission of a loop message to check if the baud rate was correctly enabled, but to my surprise, it did nothing. After a good amount of debugging time with ST-Link, I noticed that the functions HAL_CAN_Init() and HAL_CAN_Start didn’t work normally because a timer value was not updated by the HAL_GetTick() function. Upon investigating why this happened, I found that HAL_GetTick() was defined in timer.h and also in stm32f4xx_hal.h. I solved this issue by renaming the function to HAL_GetTick_openblt in all files of the OpenBLT layer. In Mexico, May 20 is the Psychologist Day, and my girlfriend is a psychologist. I forgot about it while dealing with the issue in the CAN bus. Sometimes I wish I weren’t so obsessive. If someday you read these lines, Honey, forgive me. I swear that I love you. But an engineer lost his ground debugging. May-21-24 While taking snapshots for the documentation, I noticed that if the CAN interface is enable but not connected, the bootloader never starts. This is because, in the initialization routine, it needs to be connected to a CAN bus. If you encounter this issue and don’t want to connect a transceiver, you can cross the pins CAN_Tx and CAN_Rx to initialize the bootloader. This trick can help rule out software issues. I hope this saves you some time. May-22-24 Challenge complete! Finally the system is working and the documentation is done. If you come here loking for a solution, Enjoy it! You can see the process here: OpenBLT in Nucleo-F446RE.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">After vacations!</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/14/after-vacations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="After vacations!" /><published>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/14/after-vacations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/04/14/after-vacations.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="after-vacations">After vacations</h2>
<p>After a busy work season, a break is necessary.
“Last week of February, I wanted to take a couple of days off, and I managed to get it for an indefinite period.” - Abner, my brother.
We worked as embedded software developers in the same company for a while, and unfortunately, the layoffs in high technology companies affected us.</p>

<p>I was exhausted from programming because last month at work, I had to work more than 10 hours a day just to learn how to do my tasks. However, I was laid off from my job. After these canon events I decide do some Udemy curses, pick up ciclysm again to  prepare myself phisically and mentally for a new season.</p>

<p>I took a Scrum course focused on Jira to improve these skills.
During the last week of March and the first week of April, I took a break to disconnect from computers and work.
Yesterday, I finished a course to enhance my knowledge of the Yocto Project.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After vacations After a busy work season, a break is necessary. “Last week of February, I wanted to take a couple of days off, and I managed to get it for an indefinite period.” - Abner, my brother. We worked as embedded software developers in the same company for a while, and unfortunately, the layoffs in high technology companies affected us. I was exhausted from programming because last month at work, I had to work more than 10 hours a day just to learn how to do my tasks. However, I was laid off from my job. After these canon events I decide do some Udemy curses, pick up ciclysm again to prepare myself phisically and mentally for a new season. I took a Scrum course focused on Jira to improve these skills. During the last week of March and the first week of April, I took a break to disconnect from computers and work. Yesterday, I finished a course to enhance my knowledge of the Yocto Project.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to the jungle!</title><link href="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/03/16/first-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to the jungle!" /><published>2024-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/03/16/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://razielgdn.github.io/risingembeddedmx/post/2024/03/16/first-post.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="this-is-my-first-post-to-this-blog">This is my first post to this blog.</h2>

<p>These posts will be the record of the time and troubles that I encounter when I work on a project.
You can get an idea of the duration and complexity of the project before or until you do something related.</p>]]></content><author><name>Octavio Guendulain</name><email>octavioraziel.gdn@gmail.com</email></author><category term="post" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is my first post to this blog. These posts will be the record of the time and troubles that I encounter when I work on a project. You can get an idea of the duration and complexity of the project before or until you do something related.]]></summary></entry></feed>